All
right. Hello,
welcome. It is April 16th,
2025. This is active in France stream
12.2
to and we will begin
it with making a GitHub push to the repo
that all of the work is going to be in
continuing on from
12.1 start
stream. This is going to the GitHub
repo active inference institute/
cerebrum and looking forward to people's
ideas and questions during this stream.
So this is the case of the evolving
cerebrum, the curious language of the
incident.
We're going to be using cursor IDE
version
48.9 on the native edge of
development. LLMs. The two main LLMs
that are being used uh in this
development have been Claude
3.7 and Gemini 2.5 Pro EXP 325.
So I'm just going to delete things as we
go through them and look at some
practical and some theoretical aspects
of
cerebrum. All right. So uh to begin with
and sort of to catch up on the zenotto
um the version one was uploaded on April
7th and commonalities similar topic.
Also, there was a uh script that was in
an older folder called cerebrum in the
repo that was used to assemble this the
the paper. Um, in doing that, learned a
lot about assembling papers and writing
them, expanding them. And in this
current version 1.4 release today, it's
up to 146 pages and still generated by a
single simple script, which we'll look
at in a second. um and how it's
expanded. So there's this sort of paper
component and the paper's generated
from the paper folder in the
repo. Let's look into it in cursor first
how the paper is made. Then we will look
at some cool
applied outcomes like making a linear
regression neural network and partially
observable marov decision process
model declining those into different
cases and getting different uh kinds of
behavior from different from the same
model but of different model types and
getting a little bit clearer of a view
in a few specific cas. cases what it
means to have a given generative model
in a different
case. Okay, first the paper then to the
source code and um deleting things along
the way adding things as people add
anything in the
chat. All right, first the paper
generation. Oh, and the the
documents assem uh the read me in the in
the paper folder describes this
process. Assemble paper is a script of
551 lines that looks into the component
section and assembles them into the
output. So in the output there
is the
PDF that's
generated which concatenates the title
page makes a tables of
content including all the main text
sections however many there
are and then all of the supplements
however many there
are. Um, it also outputs a pure markdown
concatenated version of the assembly
process and it
outputs an HTML version. So here's a
website rendering clickable
links still has the inserted
images. So a lot of flexibility in how
and and also the the paper and the
images are also vastly improved. So
there's multiple ways to make static
documents, interactive websites,
um, and markdown files for easy machine
reading and formatting as
well. It's generated from the components
folders. There's templates so you can
add more sections. Then there's three
folders, figures, main text, and
supplements. So in the figures are the
15 current figures and they have their
name and title. There's there's more
general ways to do it uh using latte
overleaf all these kinds of things so
that the numbering is automatic as well.
So this is kind of a fixed numbering
system but could be generalized too. So,
it has for each figure a caption, a
title, a caption, and the mermaid
markdown code to produce the figures.
Those get saved into the output as
direct
PNGs. And also, there's a graphical
abstract, which looks a little better in
PNG, which has the
figures and the abstract. So kind of
like scientific poster
style. Then there are the main text and
the supplemental information sections.
The main text is again determined by the
numbering of the file. But these are
markdown files with no mermaid diagrams
but citing the mermaid diagram for
insertion and linking. So these are
markdown files in the main text.
title page, abstract, introduction
methods, case functions and cognitive
models, model workflows as case
transformations, active inference models
and conclusion. Then there are the
supplemental
sections and if uh people have ideas for
other supplemental
uh sections to add, we can just add a
13, 14, etc.
Um, I'll open up the website just to get
a look at what's in the
supplements. Supplement one is a
mathematical details and
glossery. Supplement two breaks out the
novel proposed linguistic
cases. Supplement three focuses on
different practical
applications. Four is a bibliography
type section with related work. Five
goes into more category theory details.
Six gives future directions and road
map. Seven goes into some computational
complexity estimates for different
transformations. Eight goes into more
detail on active inference. Nine, more
information on math. 10, algorithmic
details.
11, the formal definitions of the core
linguistic cases, the main ones that are
focused on in the
paper. And section 12, uh, case study on
writing a research paper and how in
different sections of the paper,
there's different ways that sections are
used and do different things with
respect to each other and the ideas and
the reader.
So that different cases could be applied
to characterize the nature of a model or
a process in that way for those
phases. Ju just going through this last
one just as an example of a supplement
and kind of thing that if we wanted to
build another supplement someone can
make a suggestion. Precision management
in research paper writing equivalent to
learning rate, forgetting rate, um
attention, precision broadly just
describing modulatory strategies for
different kinds of upweightings and down
weightings. Message passing occurring
amongst author and manuscript, amongst
sections, manuscript and readers and
reviewers with kinds of intent oriented
um entities in different cases or using
a similar joint model of communication
in in different settings motivating why
to have cases.
writing strategies. Haven't looked into
any of these. Maybe some are useful.
Um, how to make certain kinds of pivots
rhetorically in, I guess, speech or
writing and different ways to interpret
how uh regimes of attention change with
with uh across different
sections. All
right. So that's the paper on Zenoto and
we can we can add more just to close off
this section on the paper assembly
process. There are probably other tools
to to do this more flexibly. There's
things like deep writer and a lot of
other approaches to doing structured
document generation. Building it from
scratch uh with cursor is still pretty
interesting. And having
uh plain text, multiple
sections, possibly doing um lumping and
splitting like have introduction 3.1,
3.2, 3.3, or just a more flexible way to
order the sections. It makes it really
easy to go into a section and add some
kind of feature using cursor. Like here
in the
introduction, just add one relevant
paragraph to the
end.
Structured smaller forms. figuring out
the right kinds of core graining.
Obviously, just having a dictionary
isn't writing a paper. So, having things
broken out to the word level might be
kind of a a granular way, but maybe
there's something interesting about that
format. Having a lookup table of a
dictionary and encoding sections and
words in in a totally graphical way.
just easier to write and
version. Just small updates to the
text can can be done and reviewed. So,
collaborative editing can can zoom in
and and break out different sections.
it'd be pretty clear um if there's a a
flexible ordering method or just with
the file names even if someone broke out
4 A and 4B or 4.1 4.2 updated the
assembly script etc. So okay that's the
paper.
Um next uh how about
the examples of the specific models then
the documents then anything that that
people have brought up by then
uh bigger picture how do we integrate
case-based logic so nouns in different
roles and sentences. However, treating
models as sort of noun
entities, how do we do that in theory
and
practice? Different ways to make
visuals. Mermaid's been super useful.
Maybe there's other plain text formats
that are useful too, but creating good
system and process
diagrams, structuring information from
pros and tables and
lists math with
latte. All right. Linear regression pom
dp neural networks. So this is in the
tests in in the source src folder. tests
subfolder. Let's see if code viz will
give a good representation of
this. Okay, maybe not
today.
Uh in the
tests
folder, there are uh several script
files testing each of these different
models, some utilities, and a readme.
Um the three that are fleshed out at
this point are neural network, linear
regression, active inference, POMDP.
So in each of these cases, there's going
to be a single model that gets defined
and then it's going to be
uh deployed in different
ways leading
to visualizable analyzable differences
in in outcome. So let's just look at
some of the images
first. Okay, here's a graphical summary
of how for the very same neural network,
whatever kind of of technique is being
used, there are different ways that just
considering neural network like a noun,
let alone the reference of what it
means. But there are ways that people
talk about models. That's the curious
language is the what people talk about
when they talk about models. And it's
right there in the sentence though in a
way silent in most cases in English.
There's the neural network does
something standard dictionary form
nominative. The researcher trains the
neural network like the researcher looks
at the neural network accusative case
recipient of
action. Direct and indirect similar with
dative more of like to
give rather than to look
upon
genative outputs of one of the cases
that's visible in English with the
apostrophe s
like the tables leg. So it's the outputs
of the table and these are uh it's a
different way to talk about the outputs
of something just at the first pass.
It's used in a different way in the
sentence. And then looking from the way
it's used in a sentence on up through
what the real reference is, it starts to
become a little clearer how these kinds
of sentiments that are already expressed
in natural language in method sections
in people's own inner voice and
conversations around modeling, different
ways that the words are used correlate
or relate to in this linguistic fashion
to differences in the deployment of the
model. Hence possibly regularities that
can be described and also uh structured
in ways that are are outside of these.
Okay, just the last cases here
instrumental by means of the team solves
a problem by using or with a neural
network.
Locative the patterns exist within the
neural networks layer. So referring to
the model as a location where there are
spaces within or being in time within
the model. Ablative the errors originate
from the neural network weight. It's
kind of an interesting case. Um has some
similarity with genative in some
situations. And then the vocative which
is the direct addressment like calling a
different digital assistant with a name
or calling the model to see if it exists
like a
ping. Then in each of those cases the
same neural network gets uh run with
these slight differences. So it's it's
it's pretty variable per
um okay so in the ablative case it was
discussing the errors of the model.
So in the
accusative the model was being trained.
So this is just a trace a as would be in
some other kind of machine learning
paper describing the target of
optimization like in the method section
where we say we train the neural network
to dot dot
dot. here in the dative was the giving
of
data. So this is just describing as a
function of input
distribution what do different
activations look like in the model. So
as it's being given different gifts what
patterns are
arising same neural
network here uh in the genative case is
describing uh function
outputs output distributions
Some animations of generating
output
instrumental. This might be showing
different ways that
statisticians do things with the model.
Looking at inputs, outputs, activations.
Looking at the structure of the model.
Looking at the model's training history
for a given curriculum as a kind of
empirical
data. Looking at kinds of
interpretabilities, looking at the
structure of the neural network as as
something that can be done with like
tool
engineering. All right. Locative
describing possible locations inside of
not not super
fleshed showing the model in its agentic
operation. Like when people say the
model does this, the model learns to fit
this working as active agent generating
predictions. Though those predictions
would be the predictions of so it could
be the same reference could be used in
in within one
sentence A threw the ball to B and then
B threw the ball to A. So within one
sentence or across sentences different
nouns are used in different cases and
they're marked differently from a
written from a speaking perspective in
different languages.
Similarly, models as slike nouns are
used in
sentences in different case
settings. So those have different
implications for what is viewed, what is
meant, what kind of capacities would be
required from that
model. Like does the model need to turn
on? Does it need to just give a ping
like with a vocative or does it need to
make a
prediction? So that's the neural network
example. Now there's two more examples.
There's the linear regression.
Next, so here is a y= mx +b type linear
regression. So ablative predictions
of the
model there were some very interesting
diagrams that were arising in this
linear case. So here are talking about
the model as a causal originator. So
there's the model which causes
predictions which influence or lead to
decisions which have these sort of
causal consequences.
So that's model as a source of of
causation and
prediction cross
validation here there's an evaluator who
is eval using doing something such that
they it is said that they evaluate that
model so that the model is being here
evaluated to well residuals analysis
doesn't have
anything. Cross validation in the
evaluation
phase. Here the model is in the dative
case the recipient of data like I sent I
gave a present to my friend. I sent data
to the
model and that is reflected in the batch
ingress process
with different sets of data
um or like perfective and imperfective
like the streaming online real-time data
model was receiving data in a continuous
and then the perfective like The model
finished receiving 50 units of
data. Genative
uh is like apostrophe s. So it's the
possessives of the model. So it's the
intercept of the model, the slope of the
model, mean squared error of the model.
All these kinds of
statistical expressions, things that
might be in a results
[Music]
section,
instrumental used as a instrument of
action, used as a tool like we hit the
nail with the hammer, we analyze the
data with the model. So it's doing
different again variable functional uh
images but looking at different kinds
okay so we trained this model best as we
could whether it was this or that method
and then now we're going to look at the
correlation or the causal interaction
between factors one and two and then
factors one and three and then we're
going to use that instrumentally and say
oh okay here's a 0.14
correlation and and we're this
confidence this far away from zero and
here it's this correlation. So this is
these two features are more correlated
or they have this causal
relationship. So doing things with
models
locative positions within the
model. So where is the model located in
information spaces? That's that's one
that's the kind of interpretation of the
locative and and there are multiple um
senses in which a given case is used.
But one of them was highlighted in that
neural network example which was a
location in the model like on the third
floor of the neural network. And here
that would still apply. You still could
talk about I'm talking about the y in
the equation.
And then here's another view which is
the location of the model
like they are at the store. The model is
at 2,
3. Nominative. This is sort
of even though the the uh animation
doesn't really
work. The nomin nominative is when using
the standard dictionary type sense of
the word when the model does something
like that model fit the data
that entity did
that model as actor fitting the data.
model fitting data. All the kinds of
sentences where the model is it it could
be replaced like with a person's name or
a
doer vocative. So here this has some uh
there's a few funny ways the vocative is
used. This one is in the vocative case
data points directly address the model.
So uh each point communicates its
residual value to the model line. This
direct communication visualizes the
conversation between data and models
similar to how we might address someone
by name. So this is almost at a sort of
algorithm as communication level
thinking about information processes
within like oh
-2.55 told the slope where it was and
the slope told back its residual. So
that kind of whereas in the neural
network case the vocative focused on the
addressment by name for like a digital
assistant.
Okay, here's some other vocative uses
even in linear regression. So, it's the
data and then the the model's prediction
and then is saying I I'm telling you how
far I am under the
value. Another interpretation of
algorithm as
communication where a given variable X
is saying hey slope multiply me. So x *
1.97 and then to the intercept the other
part of the mx plus b says add
4.98 and then combine us both or we get
combined or I'm the final answer after
combining. It's sort of like a
linguistic approach to describing
information flows and algorithms.
Okay, so that's the uh linear regression
model and this is all from like test
linear regression test neural
network test active inference palm
dp. So here in the in the palm dp case
um for a
given model it's being described in
different cases. So just to read the
sentences, I'll just say the model
instead of the pom dp. The model decides
which action to take next. Nominative.
The programmer evaluates the model's
performance.
Accusative. The environment gives
observations to the model.
Dative the model's belief about the
state guides decision.
Genative. We solve the problem using a
model framework. Instrumental. Different
policies exist in the model state space
locative. The new algorithm deviates
from the standard model approach
ablative and hey model what action
should I take next focative. So now
let's look through
those. Start at the bottom.
So here is a direct addressment like the
sort of digital assistant addressing a
model and and also which kinds of
functions are going to come into play.
So this gets towards uh one of the use
cases for having this type of lexical
intelligence for modeling is if one
expression block or methods block has a
bunch of vocatives then you know that
for whichever agents are addressed these
are the only commands that you need to
spin up. Whereas if it was some other
case like it making a prediction or like
you know doing forward inference might
be a different computational setup than
getting trained than getting evaluated.
So in that way just you can say like
what was happening with one actor
through a paragraph where they were
being referred to in different cases you
can trace the same model as it's being
referred to within and across sentences
in perhaps different ways in different
computational setups and and and build
for
that. Okay. So here is focusing on the
vocative nature of the call and response
between the agent and the
environment in the
nominative. So here's the model in
determination of what to do for example
by doing policy inference like expected
free energy policy selection as
inference on which actions I select
given the states and those might invoke
policy inference
methods simple 2x2 matrices for the
observation
transitions. So this is tracing out the
decision making
process looking at the palm DP as an
agent and as it's learning and updating
its belief. So what and just here just
an example animation what is its belief
and action conditional upon observation.
Okay, in the
locative here is using again the
um a little bit of a fusion of referring
to policies existing in the state space
which is pointing to the models state
space. So in that way referring to like
a location in the model. However, the
location of the mo of of the the
location of the state space in the model
may be
locationational. So
like the location parameter of the
model is in 3,
4. So here referring to the point the
phase space location. So all the kinds
of theory and empirical aspects of
saying
like the the model oscillated around a
point
attractor or the the model made its way
from thinking it was a cool day to
thinking it was a warm day. Those are
paths and passages in phase space. So
those may use verbs of motion or
locative in a certain way.
instrumental people saying stuff like we
solve the problem using the
model. So showing the
model looking at different ways in which
the model is used to explore
questions. So making predictions,
looking at phenot computational
phenotypes like the magnitude of belief
updating or the the
um different aspects of the
simulated or actual behavior of of model
being being used as a tool. Looking at
different statistical traces from the
tool. looking at error. Um,
envelopes generative is like the the the
genative AI the generative AI like the
output of
GPT or the text
wrote GPT's text the text wrote by
GPT predictions of the model the model's
predictions
Looking at the beliefs of the model.
Looking at the collection of them.
Looking at the predictions of the
model. Looking at the beliefs of the
model in relation to observations of the
model. Or it could be said in relation
to observations sent to the model. So
it' be like another way to use
observation and basically convey the
same syntax which is like we all get it.
It's getting data points
but literally as it would be with a noun
even though the two expressions the
obser as a function of observations of
the model as a function of the model's
observations is using model in the
genative as having observations that are
possessed by it or you could focus on
the the sender of the data and say that
the data were sent to or the
observations were sent or x sent object
observations to the model. So those two
features might both be true. They might
be isomorphic. They might highlight
different features of that setting. But
that's just an example uh of how many
ways there are to
map expressions about models, model
linguistics to models in in theory and
practice. Just like there's a ton of
stuff that could be said about a tree
and just the tree
grows, the leaves of the
tree, people looking at the tree, like
all those things that are kind of kicked
off by
prepositions and context. All right,
last ones for the uh POM DP and then to
the documents and then to any
uh ideas or questions people have.
here in the native environment giving
observations to the pom dp
like what it's direct indirect object
the pom dp gets observations from the
environment is having the pom dp doing
something getting and then here the
environment gives observations to the
pom
dp so looking at the impact of
observations which might describe very
well the same graphic or or related
graphic as was used. Just like the mass
of the leaves
and the branches
mass are referring to different levels
of analysis of a tree and they're using
a different case, but they still may be
very related measurements. And more
importantly, we're talking about the
same tree. So this is the same POM DP,
possibly the same run of the same POM
DP. But if you start to think about just
models as they are spoken about the
kinds of things people say about models
like first we designed the model then we
use the model to generate this then we
sent training data to the model we got
the model's errors as it's like that
kind of talking about models aspect
sometimes refers to the very same model
in the exact same situation other times
it refers to the
same lineage of model being used in
different ways. Like if it says we used
the model to sweep across this parameter
range or parameter range was swept
across those kinds of things but then
maybe only some of those parameter uh
parameterized models were taken forward
and then they were used to generate
predictions. So just it it could be a
variant of something that was described
like not exactly the same single file.
But in these simple examples, it is like
the exact same generative
model. All
right. So that's the uh a bit about the
testing suite and uh test driven
development is very effective in this
kind of augmented coding setting. It can
help lock in a lot of functions um a as
can good use of
git. Okay. Now to the doc section which
actually has many many many documents.
So uh we will definitely not look at all
them but at the top level of the docs
folder there's some information about
cerebrum just how it works this live
stream file um different features about
cerebrum maybe these will go into a
folder and then there's several folders
so starting from the smaller ones uh
dialogues these are like 17 different
genres of sort of creative
dialogue around and about some of these
different themes. So it's and and
possible to to write more. So just to
show what that looks like, just dragging
dialogues in or it could have been at
dialogues write in new dialogue that
will be very YouTube
appropriate for all the topics that are
referred to
in
paper, it is a live stream. So, make it
most
possible like most YouTube live streams
do. Okay. Discussions. This is a few
different comments that people have uh
stated related to the work and I just
responded to the um comments in writing
in GitHub just cuz it was easier to
uh express and and share
it. Examples. Uh there's just a few
examples and we can revisit this one
too. um just this can have a growing
number of specific the the linear the
linear regression but it's just
documents related to
examples. So here let's let's do a
new now there's up to three parallel
chats in
cursor.
So let's write examples up
for the
functional taking an
output. Maybe in the future these kinds
of drags will be less needed. They they
they help get it right on the first one.
Linear regression neural network
In examples, please make
three
markdowns
comprehensively for the three main tests
in
output. Have each doc example be
comprehensive. Explain why and how it
matters. Why and how cerebrum and cases
come into
play. Show not
tell. All the kinds of
things pre-addressed that anyone
thinking
seriously about this would come to
wonder initially.
Okay, back in the dialogue space.
So like that once there's a genre within
a a folder even if it's a hyper meta
genre like dialogue
um it's possible just say okay or add a
new dialogue with this
theme. Okay so that's the examples
happening. All right. Then there's the
insects folder. So, some of this may
have uh images that fail to render, but
let's look at these in
GitHub. Okay. So, here's just just
zooming in just a couple layers, just a
couple prompts deeper into all right,
how do we apply cerebrum to enmology?
So just like we were previously talking
about well the linear regression used as
a tool or the predictions of it. So this
is kind of uh classic standard ento
linguistics.
What do people talk about when they talk
about
bugs? And thinking about what what
functions, the kinds of things people do
and have and and will and would say
about
insects. Taking a first pass at the
syntax of what they
said, what are those insects being said
to do or have done to them or their
location, etc.
in that method section or in that
natural history report. So it's like are
we talking about different functional
roles different places where in
describing
that function that natural linguistic
case would be
used different speculative insect cases
mixing the sort of hyper practical
discourse analysis
uh scientific reproducibility avenue new
uh literature annotation um
hypercharging mixing with these
speculative cases like talking about the
ants pherommonal implication. That's
kind of an interesting possibility. Now,
it might be morphologically silent in
English or some other language just as
other cases are in other languages. So,
it isn't even that the words have to be
spelled any differently or pronounced
any differently. It it could just be a
situation where it's understood that the
ant as a
pherommonal actor or recipient is coming
into play. Maybe these are even over
meshed with other linguistic cases.
So different kinds of topics that come
up in ants but different aspects of
their activity
um that kind of give a
special spin or
clarity or relevance to different ways
to talk about an object under different
sorts of constraints.
looking at the ways in which this big
difference amongst languages of the
world the nominative
accusative distinguishing models acting
from models being acted upon regardless
of the actions transitivity this might
map to systems with clear initiators and
responders so the queen lays an
egg irrigative absolutive groups models
performing intransitive actions eg
moving with models receiving transitive
actions accusative distinguishing them
from models performing transitive
actions eg depositing
pheromone this might map to systems
where the state change of a model is
paramount regardless of whether it
caused or received
it like whoa
whole
onlogical
assertional
frameworks where different languages are
like falling in different ways across
these two different kinds of grammar
systems and maybe there are situations
where one or the other has a different
feature defined as all the ways in which
they're different are ways in which they
could be different in function or in
fitness in a
situation. Okay, that's the least
technical of them.
here is applying those kinds of case
depictions. Like imagine if the case
depuff or a prefix or a subscript or a
font or something like
steganographic hidden in the word or
it's just a reading lens but it's like
the projections of the neurons send data
give data to the
kaix and it's just like so again it's
not the only way to use these parts of
the brain. It's not associating them
with parts of the brain. It's like
saying there could be method sections
that use these
regions and describe these processes
using this kind of linguistics.
different computational precision
parameters and how they are in causal
relationship with sort of natural
ethological behavioral linguistics about
what is happening. Like this is a
classic Professor Deborah Gordon point
with the space between seeing the
nestmate on the ground and then
identifying the task it's doing like it
is foraging or it's part of foraging and
then going from the task identification
to the identity assertion like it is a
forager but it's like a nestmate that we
see nursing is that a
nurse is that like is a is a person
who plants trees when they're not
planting a tree still a
planter. That's more classic and to
linguistics more from the Vickenstein
side. So different ways that stigma G is
studied all these kinds of scenarios
looking at
beehive foraging looking at the
algorithms of the different ways that
information flows and processes happen
in the
relocation. Okay, insect here's more
acronyms and puns for more topics. So uh
in in the in the kind of last section as
we sort of go beyond cerebrum probably
today maybe we can use some of these or
another
one insect cognitive architectures. All
right. I was happy to see the harvester
ant pogamir max
Barbados. Um, so different
insect species and ways that they've
been studied, even though many or all
could be studied for all, but there's
just many modeledish organisms that have
been studied. Well studied
insects, looking at how different brain
regions are described of, if not playing
functional roles of using different
cases. again like are there more
mentions in the literature of we
injected the die into the projections of
the
neurons or um is the just like in the
different methods sentences of the
statistics paper it was like describing
the linear regression or the neural
network or the palm DP as getting things
done to it or doing things or being used
with all of those similarly happened for
descriptions of insect brain
regions. Different classical behavioral
types keywords for literature search
like let's do a literature search on
spatial learning plus himopa pull all
those
papers download all the papers break
them into
sentences look at every sentence do
entity extraction determine what case
different entities are in. So this is
kind of like a formal
linguistic complement to statistically
driven engram learning like classically
just taking large bodies of text and
then looking okay we could look at the
word frequency that's like the one gram
we can look at the word co-occurrence
the two gram and going on and on and on
and that kind of leads to uh you know
one thing after another to the attention
is all you need which has some kind of
engram like basically the context and
the attention mechanisms with a bit more
nuance but a lot like
that. Okay, more tables just linking up
different ways that different
functionalities, different you know what
what cases would we want to transfer
from how we talk about ants in order to
be able to say those kinds of things
about swarms of
robots. Okay, more case
studies here is more of a deep dive on
insect brain
anatomy. So looking at the different
sections of the brain in different ways,
tables looking at different
adaptations. more brain mapping, more
connection with species, behavioral
functions, neurotransmitters. So, it's
like there's again going to the
literature and annotating where those
kinds of things are said and then that
is already just sort of the forensic
cerebrum approach. It's just a purely
annotative strategy. And then also it it
implicitly and explicitly involves
sketching out these state spaces even
where some of those combinatorics are
like grammatically invalid or prohibited
for one reason or
another. Okay, not all these work. This
one doesn't
work. Different brain region, different
insect research that could be done.
Okay. Then there's two folders with a
lot of
documents. So the first one there is
languages. So languages first there's a
folder computer. Computer lang. This has
uh uh several dozen computer languages.
So let's look at go. We'll just look at
one computer language and then mainly at
natural languages.
overviews the code different kinds of
use
cases annotates the code with different
case annotations on different processes.
So you can see all of these kinds of
abbreviations. So different ways what's
one like just on looking at even just
one line of code one language might say
the data is sent to X from Y or Y sends
the data to X or just data X
Y. Not to go into this on the computer
side but the uh human
languages folder is also very rich.
There are a variety of languages. Uh
the readme is pretty much updated. Let's
just look at a few.
Espiranto. In the previous stream, we
looked at how the Hungarian case system
has onto on and from a surface. So, sort
of perfect for different functionalities
of interfaces and and boundaries.
interlavic Russian English goes into
more detail just grammatically and
cognitively on on some common first and
second language learning combinations of
Russian and English and like why certain
failures of language are common
cognitively and
grammatically. Sanskrit
Tibetan. So, Espiranto overviewing the
case just like kind of a more like a
grammar
textbook, like a really fast
summarized grammar
textbook. Sanskrit went into a bit more
uh detail here. Just several times it
would add a couple hundred lines. I'd
say awesome add more interesting, funny,
useful, meaningful
sections. So different case
[Music]
um
information different ways that a model
like an NLP model could be used
according to those cases.
grammatical number one, two, many where
some languages might only have one and
many but you know it could be helpful.
Are we talking about a single agent? Are
we talking about the diadic
communication setting or are we talking
about the more you know three three is a
party different syntactic speech
features so this could relate to if we
have a given model and just we're going
to be using Python or subscript or
special characters or prefix it's like
whatever um morphology setting you're in
with the model there might be different
kinds of of
um certain things might be easier to
express or others or might have
different consequences. All right. Then
just kept on going and just say add
more. So lots of more
um more connection
with temporal and modal systems.
So like this starts to get into the
beyond cerebrum stuff that we'll do in a
few minutes. But like there are other
parts of speech and other linguistic
techniques other than case even though
cerebrum has focused heavily on case in
these kind of two stream/ early versions
of the paper. But of course there's a
whole bevy of
conditionalities and moods and all these
different kinds of things which like
could be used to describe even just
statistical models like while this is
happening if that happens then this will
be happening at the same time as viewed
from this
perspective. So different languages have
different natural
expressivities, ways of modifying how
things look and seem. Some languages
modify certain things for sex, others
don't. Some modify for number
differently. They um of course have
different heritages and and connotations
and and different concepts that are sort
of already there. And then also they
they all have different and and
including created contrived semantic
systems as well. They
have some commonalities and differences.
So for certain kinds of computational
semantics there may be some very small
programs or some very secure ways to do
this or
that and then Tibetan. Let's just
see trust
systems, evidentiality
markers, evidential
systems, direct sensory evidence,
general knowledge or inference.
personal experience or
witness with
suffixes, direct, indirect, witnessed,
hearsay, and
inference. Also think about legal um
ontologies and and different ways that
this kind of relates there. So that's
the languages folder. There's all the
computer languages and then I mean not
every single one but that is where all
the computer languages are and the
natural languages. All right, last
folder to look at is the speculative
design. So just to show uh kind of
similarly
here. Okay, just to quickly return to
the um
examples,
let's push GitHub, go to the examples,
and then uh look at the three new that
were written just
now. POM DP, linear regression, neural
network. So introduction
laying
out what are all these different cases
about how do they apply to the palm
DP what does the demonstration
do linear
regression background on linear
regression
laying out
what is different and why it matters.
and the neural network case
similarly. Okay. In the speculative
design folder, we will add one
more document.
Okay. Dragged in speculative
design. In this
folder, write the most vast vastly
layered
comprehensive synopticon of
the just going to drag in the or I'll
just drag in the single
markdown output.
assembled
paper. Write the most and do
it
most
absurdly and information
densely in the
style of something that
strangely would make a lot of sense to
see visually on a live stream about this
topic yet be
essentially incoherent in the linear
reading. Conveying all the concepts
totally
The user wants me to create a new file
assembled
paper.
Okay, we're looking at the chain of
thought of Gemini. So called chain of
thought. They want me to create a new
file, assembled paper.md. Not really. I
didn't say that title, but let's go with
it. It should be a
synopticon. It should be visually in
interesting but incoherent.
plan. List the files. Read the files.
Synthesize the content. Create the
file. How to make it absurdly
layered. All these
different
strategies. How to make it incoherent
linear reading but make sense
visually. How to convey all the
concepts. File list. Then it lists out
the files in speculative design. It's
like, you know, it's not exactly what I
thought I wanted to know or see, but but
it's starting to get to a very
interesting
place. For each snippet, randomly or
pseudo randomly, maybe based on file
order, intersperse headings, bold terms,
list items, and short sentences, phrase
into the main synopticon string. Use
heavy markdown formatting. Prioritize
density and visual chaos over linear
coherence. Oh, brother. Ensure terms,
concepts from all files are
included. Okay.
still
going. This is just the beginning.
Incorporating elements. It's like this
is doing quite
many cycles of thinking, reading,
doing. Lots of tokens being generated
here.
But meanwhile, let's let's let's let it
cook. And uh there's a few that are
pretty fun here.
So Okay.
So, here's a Daisy Dolly Rimple um
satire uh free speech usage as they all
are where it's a sort
of early 1900s detective story and the
first part is is just story. Then it
goes into this truly delightful sequence
of uh looking at
the first off speculating some some
ancient
origins looking at the different I'll
turn off
dark looking at different
hypotheses sort of like this like
mystery science theater 3000 reading of
a Dolly
Rimple
situation talking about how in their
case in their situation in their case in
their
cases how different
processes
happened different context shifting
different processes that different ways
that
that then it kind of comes around at the
very end to uh highlight the unique
values of the different
languages and then I believe they
they call it a night and have some
Hungarian dinner. Okay, this was one
that I just said make a new speculative
design document. Go somewhere that's
that's never been done or something, you
know, glitch ontology and error-based
learning.
So it's like kind of glitch pop which
has like a visual and a
auditory. Uh so it's kind of a
multimodal
glitch but it also comes up in
programming and it's kind of a digitized
format. So like different ways that
glitchbased
methods we can fix some of
that. New tab glitch ontology fix and
improve all the mermaid diagrams.
This is probably the longest um
Gemini sequence. Oh, okay. So, it ended
there. Continue to refine the
synopicon and read all papers and then
save the final full
file.
Could be slight differences in mermaid
rendering.
Um, but cool idea. Glitch-based
ontologies like ontologies of
errors for describing systems that have
certain relationship with error.
Okay, this is a very long one but a but
an extremely worthwhile
one looking at William Blake. So it
started with just this bullet point type
stuff now starts getting into Blakeian
engineering like the four-fold vision
discussed elsewhere with single vision
being like leading up to metacognitive
integrations. So it's kind of like this
is not dissimilar than a three or four
layer hierarchical model like thought
seeds
or sanded smith type model and then it
just shows like okay which model in that
four-fold
vision
paradigm going into detail like this is
kind of like the retinal layer with the
convolutional neural networks dropout
layers that kind of stuff because it's
like the sensory so it's like multi-cale
higher hierarchical
architectures, possible self- similarity
of the two, three, and four-fold visions
in terms of their their capacities going
into the
zoas looking at cognitive functions of
the the integrated albon and the
different kinds of
functionalities fractal self similarity
with eternity in an hour. How would that
really get implemented?
um different
cosmological
parallels. What would really be
different with a Blake inspired cerebrum
using AI?
Well, single objective, contrary,
balancing, multi-objective like to to
target the m the creation and
maintenance of tension or
paradox architecture
detailed architecture
layers. So it's kind of like there's the
does this accurately describe what
Tharmmas is in the Blakeian ontology.
That's kind of like a separate question
that's interpreting this just as like
structured humanities research and just
is that uh mer of the different places
this box could be pointing or connected
to. Does that align? And and surely
there's multiple uh takes even for one
character and then it's like what are
the functional attributes of this kind
of architecture. So what is that
transfer path from loose or ambiguous or
or multiple or even
contradictory poetic description and
basically all of these kinds of
information
processes generation reality layer the
lua generative layer that's the two-fold
vision three-fold vision golanuza
creative layer and then the Eden
integration
Okay, there's just too many funny
things. This this was a funny one. The
eternity sunrise development. So
2025, this very year implement the core
zoa's architecture begin contrary
processing research. So little different
spin than predictive processing. Okay.
Contrary processing research. Hm. But
that's that sort of unity is plural at
minimum two research agenda. But then
that's also the paradox. Well, but then
isn't the single objective unity is
plural at minimum two? So how how to
hold the one and the two? That's like
the single and the two-fold vision. Then
over the years leading to 2029
eternity
sunrise self-evolving cognitive
architecture begin Albon
integration more sections
then really nice process diagrams super
information
dense looking at at different and being
able to do programmatic generation
archetypal description
of logistics for perception action
cycles. So this is kind of like a whole
cognitive sequence. It's not just saying
well there's a for loop that gets an
observation and then uh puts out an
action or it's like an observation comes
in
this parallel processing like marriage
of heaven and hell status
occurs certain sequences happen then
there's a back and forth here and then
this all
etc. It could be make a dynamic control
flow in the marriage of contraries.
Let's
do make a vast comprehensive dynamic
control
flow
with massive level of detail
of process
diagrams. Something com
completely
capturing the spirit of
James
Joyce. All the most
chaotic
and
[Music]
Riverrunesque stuff.
Also do the same in
another design
file for cerebrum plus infinite
jest. Okay. Wow. Still
plugging on that. Those are almost
certainly the two very longest
um executions I've ever seen from
Gemini for for for the sheer number of
uh
steps. Okay. Then the last one before we
push those updates look at the new ones.
This was uh as per the uh request of a
friend on John D who lived from 1527
to608.
So I was not extremely familiar with D
but this was a really interesting
approach that brought together those
process diagrams
um different kinds of cgraphy spatial
computing time
cryptography secure
communications. So it's kind of like
John D's
work transferring
onto what what was said in that work and
what has been said about that
work onto the specification of
cryptographic or of like esoteric
semantic components.
Correspondence
tables, active inference topics,
category theory
[Music]
terms, different
ciphers. We can do a
whole Okay, that was okay. That was it.
Did the
full assembled
paper. Make
a
vast speculative design document on
using cerebrum
or cryptographic
design,
syntax,
semantics, cognitive narrative.
This one halted
early. Okay, let's look at the assembled
paper.
Okay. Synopticon.
This was prompted again to be incoherent
to read out loud but to give a lot of
information when visually looked at
Okay, let's look at those the joy and
infinite chest. Then we'll look at the
live chat. If anyone has an idea or
question, then go into the sort of
beyond.
So here it didn't make the file, but
that's what's so fun about
cursor. Put that and improvements and
additions into a file with the right
name. And also this chat is getting
long. So that's why there's this start a
new chat for better results down there.
Okay, push these
Okay. Joyce and Jest.
Okay. Infinite
chest. First one doesn't
work. Basian funhouse
mirrors. This sounds clean. It rarely
is.
Okay. And the
joist. I don't think I can evaluate the
details, but you
know, it's
cool.
Okay. And there's the cryptographic.
That's what you know again it just it's
the concept. It's it's the possibility
that these spaces can be defined up
front or on the fly and they can be
passed to the right other agents or
people or just generated from scratch or
in the future in a better way.
Okay. Okay. So the main piece to sort of
leave a
little snippet of again in this last
part it's going to be just a few uh
what's next in our path and then if
anybody has a idea or a question live
chat that they can write
it.
So, let's go
into a whole new
folder beyond
cerebrum. Beyond
spec.
So given all
that information on cerebrum and all it
can do
with grammatical
case. Let's zoom out and think beyond
it.
Let's come up with insects or other
invert related
acronyms to
conveying
absolute total scope of what can be
considered a quote
full linguistic intelligence method.
whereby all
the parts of
language,
verb,
noun, all parts of speech, moods,
etc.
are
firstly formalized into the kind
of
operations which
flexibly can and do apply to eg linear
regression neural
network basian graphical
model. Then in that case with full
formalization we are only in
the tip of the
iceberg in terms
of xeno and exol linguistics.
Firstly come to totally understand
that then spec out
completely this quote beyond cerebrum
effort. Okay. planning a
response.
Pormica H. That's a that has a nice ring
to it.
Myriad, Mantis,
Apis, Locust, Vespa, Arachnne,
Silk. All good.
Okay. Formica Locust
Arachnne. Let's go with Formica. Okay.
First idea is the best one.
continue just even just pre pre-prompt
pre-writing what I I believe or expect I
will want to say soon or
next with all
needed files
for
functions underpin Ed by
same functions described in
core beyond spec document which is
always growing and
improving
iteratively such
as forensic
work
describing the
lexical environment of a model in time
in place in use.
All modern machine
learning cutting edge
questions
interpretability scaling
safety
pure enmological
linguistic pragmatism.
Wow. Already jumping to the tools that
you know it could be a it could be a
uh Wow. I've never seen a chain of
thought that looked like
this.
Create directory
structure. Okay. Source a source folder
within. Then
update the
spec. Create the init
scripts. Add a readme. Okay. Now this is
the what? This is the part I've never
seen. Constraint checklist and
confidence. Follow cursor rules. Yes.
Here's the cursor
rules. One funny prompt in another
setting was like, "Write yourself a
prompt that will lead you to generate
the prompt that will help you generate
the greatest, most accurate, relevant,
possible cursor rules file
set.
Okay. So it's like this is kind of where
Q kids and catechisms come into play
which is
just developing these sets of questions.
So it's like oh yeah that's the Q78 or
like oh you you could you could just use
the use the Q600 ask all those figured
out you know.
Okay
placeholder for lexical environment. So
for this one we can uh download we could
scrape uh papers or scrape websites and
then use anything from rulebased methods
to existing software packages to LLM API
calls to say okay given what we know
about cerebrum and whatever this form or
whatever system is given that what are
the entities what cases are they
Yes, given the structure now
then comprehensively continue so that
all
docs formal specs of
the parenthesy more
than
language formal type
theory category
calculus and
basian cognitive functions are 100%
100%.
It's not sort of where
I hope to and will go over the coming
little bit uh with anyone's open source
participation if they're if they're
interested listening along this far.
Let's read that doc.
Okay. Cerebrum provides a powerful
framework for integrating case-based
reasoning and basian
representations, focusing significantly
on the role of grammatical case in
structuring meaning and reasoning. While
valuable, case grammar represents only
one facet of the complex system that is
human or potentially non-human language.
To achieve a truly comprehensive
computational understanding of
linguistic intelligence, we must expand
our scope
significantly. New chat
tab. Speculative design.
looking
past even future horizons.
Write a vast
comprehensive speculative
design doc
with valid mermaid diagrams
and tabular
intelligence about
what
gle
maximalism really means.
parenthesy in group discussion
only.
Okay.
Okay. Define base types for fundamental
linguistic units. Phony, morphe, lexical
item, syntactic constituent, semantic
concept, pragmatic
concept, composite
types, dependent
types, connections to formal grammar
frameworks. Laying out those types
research challenges
relation.
Okay, but
just continue. I'll start a new chat for
better
results. Continue
comprehensively with developing
Have all needed documents in fractal
docs folder. Have all source code and
tests. Start running and developing the
full
simple modular test suite now.
Okay. Okay. Question from the
chat. What kind of predictions might you
have about case users? across
disciplines, experience in a field or
experience with the
language. What would it reveal if case
use was different across
groups?
Okay. And another question live
chat. Can we me can we mechanically
deform the cranium to 10x the cerebrum?
Um, probably. But you probably couldn't
get it back,
Tucker. But I think I think with a 3D
printer and a shipping container, it
could be
possible. What would reveal if case use
was different across groups? Yeah,
there'll be so many interesting topics
like the uh discovered slashinvented
uh question of case to what extent are
two on at from of an object fundamental
aspects of semantics. Are there other
fundamental aspects of semantics that
we get through or get around in human
language in other ways? I think that at
the very least a first step, not the
only first step, um not not the not the
last step, but a first step is this kind
of beyond cerebrum approach where it's
like first get the full interoperable
category theoretic calculus type, you
know, algebra, etc., etc., etc. for all
the languages that we know about.
partially to scaffold and improve the
fluency of people and LLMs, partially to
understand well what are all the state
spaces and then if we find that there's
something where there's always exactly
three in every language even if they
were all the same we could still say
like well what if it was four or maybe
we'll find that there's um one two and
many for marking numbers in one language
and another one it's one two three and
many another one it's just one and many
or another one doesn't have that
distinction it's
any of those even just seeing two
examples is kind of like the arc
challenge. It's like you see that uh
this could have been this way or that
way and then there's a whole state space
that it could be. So there could there
could be a
uh uh special numerosity for multi- aent
models where it's like there's a
subscript for how many agents there are.
But it can it can have, you know, 50
subscripts coming out of every corner,
different fonts, all these different
kinds of modifications. And that's just
typographically, let alone how it's
spoken or how it gets rendered
computationally where it doesn't even
need to be limited by like how many
suffixes can you add or or how many um
subscripts would make sense in uh your
your word processor. It's about these
like higher
order modifications. So when people say
I'm talking about sending the data to
the affective active inference models
API that could be something that gets
fully fleshed out maybe static analysis
on certain components but certainly for
scientific integrity full
reproducibility understand what is that
category of models and so that is
the curious language of the incident
which is for the incident which
motivates
languaging. What is the curious
languages that let that semantics get
communicated?
Okay, some more great questions from
Tucker. We
will make documents.
Okay.
Okay. It seems like human language
taking a survey of different semantics
and grammarss around the world doesn't
need case and that even semantic density
is not specifically correlated to case
versus no case structure. Yeah, it's
it's highly possible that um by kind of
sandpapering the language of the
exoteric markers of case like English
for the most part it it it could be
associated causally or just
correlationally with an increased or
decreased information density. So
consider different ways like per phone.
Um whereas like if you're doing stem
modifying like a Slavic language then
maybe there's only so many modifications
that you can overlap. If you're doing
suffixing then maybe you can have more
but you know suffixing might lead to
very long symbol
density. Then again if there's a certain
number of symbols that are needed for
the subscripting you know just so there
it's I I don't think there's a single uh
answer especially in the absence of
empirical evidence. uh in our in our uh
hands and mandibles. But we could say
write a speculative
design
dissertation
summary of all the
situations where human languages with
and without different case systems would
and would not have different information
densities.
and
designs considered
at syntax, semantic, narrative,
cognitive
levels.
Okay. Fill in all placeholder methods.
Start to run
log confirm the test suite
formica. Okay. Gle maximalism. Oh
wow. Being a little bit um recalcitrat
to write this document despite its
absolutely benign cellular nature.
Write that and improve that into a
file.
Okay. Okay. Tucker wrote, "Why do so
many ancient languages send? I don't
know what us is."
Usakri You Scotty.
Oh, thank you for that. That we should
add this to languages.
Oh, it is there as Basque
Uscara. Why do they have no chill? I
don't
know. Now fully write out that
dissertation.
Tons of tabular
formatted crystal good stuff. Parenthesy
information. Vast technical mermaid
diagrams. Unique explanations and
predictions.
Unknown and unknown to
linguists in 2025.
Wow. Still still dragging heels on the
gle
component. Maybe switch to
Claude. Oh, great question. Great
question. Let's ask
perplexity. Okay. Tucker wrote, "Are any
modern languages in widespread use
gaining in case
complexity?" Let's do the perplexity
research.
case
evolution today
MD. Okay, that's interpreting
that. Okay.
research
and fully empirically address this
question from my good
friend. The answer must ring in his
ears like gold and
silver. And he is a refined listener.
He
expects only the finest
information. Okay. Meanwhile,
Perplexity, let's do the slower or the
faster mode of
Plexity. I don't know.
Yeah, that would be
uh this is kind of a uh one one approach
that could be
used beast which is basian evolutionary
analysis by sampling tree. Let's write
out this document. This is going to
be
beast case
analysis.
Okay, I'm just going to copy in just one
paragraph about
beast. Oh, we have so much good stuff
happening though.
Okay, that one will finish
soon. That one will finish soon. Let's
just see where he got with the
development. Yeah, making good progress
on Formica.
Okay, with this description of
beast, write up a fully
technical
NSF
posttock
proposal for
using cerebrum and formica parenthesis.
Please lift them up if you
need to
do ancestral
state basian
phenotypic
reconstruction of ancient linguistic
elements. We are going way into the
past. We will use generative AI as
needed for creating
create creating fluent
text,
audio and
visual
media. Given
the explicit
probabilistic models and empirical data,
we will be
compiling and inferring on
ancient
and contemporary
languages. Okay. Cleo
maximalism. Oh, it's
okay. It says it's for internal
discussion only. I feel like I could
share it here though. But we'll reset
that
chat. Go back to
Gemini. Write it out
fully. The full posttock
application. Thank you.
Okay. Gle
archetypes. Oh, this will look better
on. Okay. Test
infrastructure. Okay. We stop the agent
after 25 calls. Continue.
Look at the
gle tests
developing writing the that posttock
application.
Okay, but to Tucker's
question, most linguists agree that
human languages tend to simplify their
case systems over time rather than
develop more complex ones. Of course,
just like in genomic and uh phenotypic
settings. It's like wait, but then how
was there a more complex one? The
historical trend seen in Indo-Uropean
languages has been towards case
reduction, not expansion.
Latin, old English, old East Slavic and
Sanskrit. All of them have dropped in
cases. Are we buying the dip with
respect to case number? I don't know.
Maybe it could go down
further. Not not financial advice, not
linguistic
advice. Okay. Counter evidence.
Virtually no documented examples of
modern widely used languages have
developed more complex
systems as on 11 wrote in languages
cases usually die out. It's a known
process. Why would they appear instead
of disappearing? Right? Why would they
appear instead of disappearing?
Absolutely. Perplexity. Let's see.
There's no strong evidence that a modern
language but but
but could could a language with more
cases gain more
popularity. Are any languages gain case?
But English is right now rare but
possible. Oh, they debate about Mandarin
Chinese.
Okay. Deeper
research. Okay. But you now you you know
what I am going to ask next. If
that case
reduction is such a slam
dunk that it
is
pervasive today. Give me the
most
complete parenthesy and
esoteric account of how those
complex
many systems ever even came to be.
Okay, gal
cells. Okay, so centering the role of
the GA and then there's the neuronal
processing layer, but it's like we we
don't really talk about those in GIA
science. It's more about the kind of
multiple types of
GA micro gal
criticism. Okay. So that's kind of like
the
feedback. Okay.
centering the role of the oligodendrite
between
neurons using
formica in the sort of neural semantics
of
Gal. Okay.
The emergence of elaborate case
paradigms and languages such as
protoindo-uropean pi Sanskrit and finick
languages involve layered
grammaticalization processes and socio
linguistic
factors. The pi case system. So this is
the one that is mostly used in
cerebrum. The system likely arose
through spatial and semantic
differentiation but I repeat myself.
Analogical extension case markers
originally tied to specific semantic
roles. Instrumental for tools expanded
to abstract syntactic functions.
Phonological reinforcement. Sound
changes eroded distinctions between
stems prompting speakers to innovate new
markers to avoid
ambiguity. Stable case systems.
Oh, some languages did have expanded
case complexity. I mean, like maybe
Hungarian or some of these other
ones. The dative plural um persisted due
to its role in marking indirect
objects. Yeah, interesting. But a little
little but but that's
exactly that's exactly what we can
analyze with
this postto application that we're
writing just like you could use beast to
look at the genomic or phenotypic
patterns. Okay.
Run the
full Formica test
suite. Develop and improve the Formica
tests, methods,
visualizations, animations,
documentation.
Okay. Okay.
Vastly expand the
NSF postto
application.
Add comprehensive
tables, specific explanations and
predictions
in huge valid mermaid diagrams.
Okay, still plugging away on
Formica. Okay, we're going to get this
Postto application
done, read it on GitHub, see if anyone
else um has any questions or ideas in
the live chat, and then call it a day.
Okay. Yes.
develop
everything
fully run and improve that test suite
which
yields full computations and
visualizations.
Okay. Right.
Just save
that. a few improvements on this kind of
stuff with like the need to reapply
tools and
uh better situational awareness for the
codebase reading folder structures kind
of doing better in uh that could be
partly in cursor partly uh other other
approaches. All
right. Speculative design
beast. Okay.
Reconstructing ancient linguistic
phenotypes using integrated basian
modeling and casebased reasoning
enhanced by generative
AI. Okay. intellectual
merit pioneering the use of generative
AI specific generative AI model name eg
GBT4
tacoron I'm
sorry it is an end to end text to speech
tacoron broader impacts
Okay. Oh, that's going to cost
you
foil. Yes.
Lexicon swadesh
lists.
Perfect. It's like there's just so much
to learn. A lot of it is out
there. A Swedesh list is a list of forms
and concepts which all languages without
exception have terms
for. Okay. New file just
dropped. Swadesh
list. Yes. Run the test suite and add
tests that show off and
visualize
for new
chat. Write a swadesh list for
cerebrum and formica as
language. Okay, thank you Tucker. Then
write another
file
meta swadesh list
markdown both maximum length
and accuracy.
Yeah, cursor writing these terminal
commands, running the pi test by
itself. Super big speed up, super
effective. Okay, hyper swadesh. That
could be
next. Morris
suadesh. He started with a list of 215
meanings. falsely introduced as a list
of 225 meanings in the paper due to a
spelling error. Yeah, hate to see that
happen.
Whoa. Wow.
Great topic to have.
Okay, this is the
swadesh
minimal minimal terminology. Who, what,
what, where,
when all could be
associated
develop
further and
furthermore the
swadesh list include all swadesh
terms and add
case annotation.
Okay. Then the meta meta
swadesh. Oh then. Okay. Clearly there
has been a kind of
misunderstanding.
A
meta-wadesh list is like a swad list for
such
lists. A list of all the
criterion you'd use in the production or
inference productions or inference of
a Suadash
list coming to a file near you.
Okay, Formica is up and
running. Add a
visualization script for
Formica. Ensure that running
The test
suite
yields
copious accurate visualizations and do
gif.
Okay. You're doing okay with the sweat
dashless.
Okay, let's look at this. What the the
the the first the layer one Swedesh
list the
L1. Yes, perfect. Like this is the basis
of what we need for Formica, which
is what what are the what are the 200 or
so concepts that we need in
Formica
for total ant colony modeling?
What are their parts of
speech here? Nest core their forage
zone. So it's like home and away like
over here over
there. Many many
mandibles. Other alien scent.
One, two, three, four,
five. Yeah, I guess you don't even need
six. Maybe you call that just like le
legish or
something. Okay. Different different um
different creatures in the
nest. Okay. body
parts,
actions, natural
colors, adjectives,
directions.
Great.
Okay. Okay, now we're on the right page
with the meta swadesh
list. Now write that meta swad list
fully. 200 concepts or so
please.
Yeah, run the test.
Suite confirm and log where
visualizations are
made. Okay, I understand you want a
significantly more detailed and
exhaustive breakdown of criteria,
principles and considerations related to
swadesh
lists.
Okay.
Okay. Our
next album
MD. Okay. New
chat. Prediluvian Super Swadesh is the
name of our next
album. Write out all the song names and
lyrics and in call
outs describe the that
sound. Okay. Meta swadesh list. We're
there. It really did go up to It It
really did go up to
207. See
also external resources on Swadesh
lists, Lexico statistics and GLTO
chronology. Write another comprehensive
document on glto chronology.
Okay. Okay. 27 tests. Looks
like beyond cerebrum is coming together.
Let's see where it's saving things
to. Yes. Run the script and then run a
terminal
command to confirm where the
visualization saved to.
Glauto chronology is a controversial
method within historical linguistics
that aims to estimate the time depth
since two or more related languages
separate from a common ancestor. It
attempts to do this by quantifying the
degree of laxore placement within a
specific subset of core
vocabulary.
Yeah, I think basian methods could help
a lot
there. Okay. our
album. We're gonna look at this album on
GitHub. All right, this is going to be
this will be the last piece. I think
people get it. It's possible to um go
beyond cerebrum in like a 20 minute
period.
Okay, we'll close with this. The
pre-diluvian super
swadesh. Silt speaks first. Primordial
murmur. Obsidian shards on the
shore. The cgraphers's
dream. That's an
instrumental. Occasional occasional
sonar pings or distorted radioatic hint
at failed surges and forgotten
geographies. Whispers from the
ziggurat's
core arc construct gopherwood and pitch
40 days delusion.
Dissolution ararat landing new soil old
son.
Well, hope this has
been a
uh interesting stream for people.
Uh, it's all Creative Commons BY
NCD. So, if you want to work on it, feel
free to make contributions to the repo.
If you want to collaborate on a future
part of the Formicus stack, there's uh
there's always a always a
way and we should
be we should be on our way.
Okay, that's it. Looking forward to
people's comments. Thank you, Gia
Maximalist and Jeff and Tucker for the
live
chats.
Okay, bye.